Guide to the Lefferts family papers ARC.145
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 2: Lefferts Businesses, 1783-1882; 0.25 Linear Feet in 1 document box.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically according to business name. General receipts, particularly business related to the farm, can be found at the end of the series.
  The Lefferts Businesses series contains documents related to the operation of several businesses which the Lefferts family ran or had an interest in. The majority of the materials in this series concern transportation infrastructure companies that operated in Brooklyn such as the Jamaica and Flatbush Turnpike Company, the Gravesend and Coney Island Bridge and Road Company and the Brooklyn, Flatbush, and Coney Island Railway Company. Many of these companies were involved in creating the early transportation infrastructure of Kings County some of which is still used today. The Jamaica and Flatbush Turnpike, for example, is one of the oldest roads in Kings County. The materials include receipts, account ledgers, stock and bond certificates, and indentures. The series also contains some receipts and other records concerning the operations of the Lefferts farm and other official business carried out by the Lefferts family in Brooklyn. More materials related to Lefferts businesses and accounts can be found in the Lefferts Family series, particularly material related to the Lefferts farm, tenants, land acquisitions and transfers.
  - Brooklyn, Flatbush, and Coney Island Railway Company, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Flatbush Plank Road Company, 1853-1865 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Account ledger, 1858-1865
  - Gravesend and Coney Island Bridge and Road Company, 1802-1853 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Five indentures, 1823 and 1826
  - Jamaica and Flatbush Turnpike Company, 1810-1811 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Receipts: Farm and Business, 1783-1841 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series 3: Lefferts House and Ephemera, 1728-1938; 0.25 Linear Feet in 1 document box.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically according to description.
  The Lefferts House and Ephemera series consists of materials which are specifically related to the upkeep and functioning of the Lefferts Historic House Museum, items accumulated by the museum with no immediately clear connection to Lefferts family members, and other ephemera from the collection.
  The Household Goods Inventories give accounts of furniture, textiles, and other three dimensional objects which were part of the Lefferts house prior to its move to Prospect Park. The "General Small Items" and "Manuscripts and Poems" are all items which were between the pages of Lefferts books or mixed in with other Lefferts documents without credit to their source. This series also holds some items connected to the Lefferts outside of the Lefferts Historic House Museum. The brochure on "Brookwood" refers to once Virginia home of Mary Gray Lefferts and the report from the Lefferts Manor Association refers to association of the landmarked area within the Prospect-Lefferts Gardens neighborhood of Brooklyn. This series also includes some hand-written recipes used by Cornelia Stuyvesant. More recipes can be found in the cookbooks in the Books and Scrapbooks series.
  - Astronomical Almanac, 1771 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Brooklyn Sunday School Union, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Brookwood: A Virginia Country Home, booklet (inscribed: Residence of Mary Gray Lefferts), circa 1910s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera: General Small Items, circa 1860s-1910s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Ephemera: Manuscripts and Poems, circa 1800s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Household Goods Inventory, circa 1800s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Household Goods Inventory for Fire Insurance, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lefferts Manor Association: Reports, History, and Directory Booklet, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Mayor's Committee of Welcome to Home-Coming Troops Booklet, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - New England Weekly Journal, 1728 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Old Dutch House Preservation Committee, circa 1920 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Playing Cards (Swiss scenic aces), circa 1860s-1890s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Recipes used by Cornelia Stuyvesant, circa 1900s (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Reformed Dutch Church of Flatbush: Quarter-Millennial Anniversary Booklet, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Series 4: Genealogical Material, circa 1720s-1930s; 0.75 Linear Feet in 1 document box and 2 oversized boxes.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically according to family names in the description. At the end of the series one can find a general list of baptisms and marriages by Reverend Dr. Schoonmaker.
  The Genealogical Material series includes records of births, deaths, and marriages that are among the Lefferts family materials. The majority of the materials are related to the Lefferts family and its branches including some members of the Cortelyou, Lott, Vanderbilt, Van Pelt, Haughwout, Lloyd, and Hegeman families. Some of these lists were taken from loose pages inserted into the Lefferts family Bibles but there is also a book including a chart genealogy of eight generations of the Lefferts-Haughwout family and the visually impressive Marshall Lefferts family tree circle genealogy.
  Most of the material in the series is related to the above-mentioned Brooklyn families but there is also Reverend Dr. Schoonmaker's Book of Marriages and Baptisms which includes a listing of many others who were baptized or married in Brooklyn.
  Some genealogical notes of births and deaths may be remain on the flyeaves not pulled from some of the books in the Books and Scrapbooks series. The Books and Scrapbooks series also includes a copy of Teunis G. Bergen's Genealogy of the Lefferts family, 1650-1718.
  - Cortelyou, Lott, and Lefferts Families: List of Marriages (1750-1780), Undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Cortelyou, Vanderbilt, and Van Pelt Families: Notebook with Births, Deaths, and Marriages (1590s-1934), circa 1934 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Lefferts and Haughwout Families: Births and Deaths (1678-1766, transcribed from bible of Leffert Lefferts), circa 1800s (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Lefferts-Haughwout Family: Chart Genealogy in Eight Generations (by Leferd Herle Alexander), 1903 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Lefferts and Hegeman Family: Births and Deaths List (1720-1829), circa 1720-1829 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Pages from the Dutch Bible of Femmetie Lefferts and Lefferts Cooke family, 1741. See Series 8: Books and Scrapbooks.
  - Lefferts and Hegeman Family: Birth, Death, and Marriage Lists (1719-1829), circa 1789-1829 (Box OS 1, Item 8)
    Though these pages were found in the Lefferts' Universal Family Bible by Rev. Benjamin Kennicott (see Series 8: Books and Scrapbooks), the pages are not originally from that book and likely torn from an earlier bible that is not within the collection.
  - Lefferts and Lloyd Families: Births and Deaths Lists (1740s-1840s, transcribed from the bible of Louise Zabrieskie), circa 1920s (Box 4, Item 20)
  - Lefferts Family: Births, Deaths, and Marriage List (1780-1829), circa 1780s-1830s (Box OS 1, Item 9)
  - Lefferts, Lott, Ryserson, and Schenck Families: Births, Deaths, and Marriages (1676-1804), circa 1670s-1800s (Box OS 1, Item 10)
    These pages are from the Lefferts family's Dutch bible, 1637. See Series 8: Books and Scrapbooks.
  - Marshall Lefferts Family Tree: Circle Genealogy (1640s-1876, prepared by Augusta McKesson), 1913 (Box OS 2, Item 3)
  - Reverend Dr. Schoonmaker's Book of Marriages and Baptisms (1800-1847), circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Series 5: Maps, 1794-1890s; 1.25 Linear Feet in 1 document box and 1 oversized box.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by description.
  The Maps series contains eight different maps including maps that are clearly related to the Lefferts family and those that are not. Of particularly note is the broadside advertisement for the sale of land owned by John Lefferts (1826-1893) in Flatbush. Two versions of this map are included, one unmarked and one marked with "Sold" stamps in some of the 500 lots that were for sale. Several other surveyor maps are included in the series, though two include unknown areas. Also included is a map related to the Battle of Long Island detailing the position of the troops of British General James Grant.
  - Broadside Advertisement For Land Owned by John Lefferts, sale of "500 select lots", Town of Flatbush, bounded by East New York Ave, Fenimore Street, Rogers Avenue, and New York Avenue, 1887 (Box OS 3, Folder 2)
  - General Grant's Position on Long Island (engraved for Stedman's History of the American War), 1794 (Box OS 3, Folder 3)
  - Hookers New Pocket Plan of the City of New York, 1821 (Box OS 3, Folder 4)
  - State of Rhode Island, hand-drawn map, circa 1800s (Box OS 3, Folder 5)
  - Surveyor Map: Area Approximately Bounded by Flatbush Avenue, East New York Avenue, and Bedford Road, hand-drawn, circa 1800s (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Surveyor Map: Unknown Area, bordered by land of Neefus, Williamson, and Schoonmaker, circa 1800s (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Surveyor Map: Unknown Area, includes scale and pictorial relief, circa 1780s-1890s (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Series 6: Graphic Materials, circa 1800s-1970s; 2.25 Linear Feet in 1 document box and 7 oversized or odd-sized boxes.
  The Graphic Materials series is divided into three sub-series, Sub-Series 1: Lefferts Graphic Materials, Sub-Series 2: Brooklyn and New York City Graphic Materials, and Sub-Series 3: Other Graphic Materials. See the not on each sub-series for the arrangement of its materials.
  The Graphic Materials series contains images of a variety of subjects related to the Lefferts family, the Lefferts house, Brooklyn, New York City, and New York State. The genre of materials includes photographic prints, tintypes, daguerreotypes, glass plate negatives, photo albums, picture postcards, and prints of engravings. The series does not include maps or scrapbooks which can be found in Series 5: Maps and Series 8: Books and Scrapbooks respectively. The series has been broken down into three sub-series: Sub-Series 1: Lefferts Graphic Materials, Sub-Series 2: Brooklyn and New York Graphic Materials, and Sub-Series 3: Other Graphic Materials. See the individual scope notes below for each sub-series for descriptions.
  - Sub-Series 1: Lefferts Graphic Materials, circa 1850s-1970s; 0.75 Linear Feet in 1 document box and 5 oversized or odd-sized boxes.
    Sub-Series 1: Lefferts Graphic Materials contains the images that are created by, depicting, or related to the Lefferts family and the Lefferts house. Individuals have been identified where possible, but many are yet to be identified. Among the figures who have been identified are Eliza Lefferts Cooke, Louise Lefferts Downs, John Lefferts (1785-1829), James Lefferts (1855-1911) and Jacobus Lefferts (1757-1799). The sub-series also includes two photo albums with photographs of Lefferts family members. In addition to the historic Lefferts house, this sub-series also contains images of the houses of Rem Lefferts, the Lefferts Vanderbilts, the Fanning branch of the Lefferts family in Sterling, Illinois, and the Virginia home of Mary Gray Lefferts.
    - Bloom-Lefferts House and Family (front and back of house, Robert Benson Bloom), circa 1860s-1890s (Box OS 4, Folder 1)
    - Civil War Soldiers (including John McKessen, Jr. [1840-1924], nephew to Marshall Lefferts), circa 1861-1865 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Cooke, Eliza Lefferts, circa 1860s-1910s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Downs, Louise Lefferts, circa 1900-1920 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Fanning Family, circa 1860s-1910s (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Fanning Home (Sterling, IL), circa 1860s-1910s (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Hegeman Deed from Peter Stuyvesant: Glass Plate Negative, Undated (Box OS 5, Item 1)
    - Lefferts Bellport House, Undated (Box Mold 1, Item 1)
    - Lefferts, Carrie Alexander and Children (Louise, Eliza), circa 1890s-1920s (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Lefferts, Charles and Lizzie (of Iowa), circa 1870s-1890s (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Lefferts, Eliza J., circa 1860s (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Lefferts, Eliza J.: Daguerreotypes, circa 1860s (Box Daguerreotypes 3)
    - Lefferts Family: Photo Album (small), circa 1860s-1900s (Box OS 6, Item 1)
    - Lefferts Family: Photo Album (large), circa 1860s-1900s (Box OS 6, Item 2)
    - Lefferts Family: Unidentified Persons, circa 1860s-1910s (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Moved to Oversize Box 4:
      - One oval photograph on cardboard of man in suit with mustache.
    - Lefferts Family: Unidentified Persons, Daguerreotypes, circa 1850s-1900s (Box Daguerreotypes 3)
    - Lefferts Family: Unidentified Persons, Tintypes, circa 1860s-1900s (Box Tintypes 1, Folder -)
    - Lefferts House, circa 1910s-1970s (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Two photos of Lefferts House (6.5"x4" and 7.5"x10") posted on cardboard
    - Lefferts House: Barn, Glass Plate Negative, Undated (Box OS 5, Item 2)
    - Lefferts House: Carrie Lefferts Photos, Lincoln Road, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Lefferts House: Historic American Building Survey, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Lefferts House: Photo Album, circa 1910s-1930s (Box OS 4, Item 3)
    - Lefferts, Jacobus (1757-1799), Undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Lefferts, James (1855-1911), circa 1900-1910 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Moved to Oversize Box 6:
      - One glass negative of James Lefferts in doorway
    - Lefferts, John (1785-1829), Undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Long Island Homes: Illustrated Calendar, 1926 (Box OS 4, Item 3)
    - Picture Postcards, 1904-1911 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - "Polly" [parrot], circa 1910s (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Rem Lefferts House (1224 Fulton Ave), circa 1900-1910 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Somers House (Cobham, Virginia), circa 1880s-1920s (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Vanderbilt House (of Gertrude Lefferts Vanderbilt), circa 1824-1902 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Virginia Country Home, circa 1800s (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Sub-Series 2: Brooklyn and New York City Graphic Materials, circa 1800s-1939; 0.75 Linear Feet in 1 document box and 2 oversize boxes.
    Sub-Series 2: Brooklyn and New York Graphic Materials contains many scenes of Brooklyn and New York City. Many of these images were likely collected by the Daughters of the American Revolution during their stewardship over the Lefferts Historical House Museum. Many of the images are reproductions of etchings which themselves reproduce earlier artwork. Many of the recreated views of Brooklyn, including views of Fulton Avenue, Flatbush Avenue, Atlantic Avenue and the Old Stone House at Gowanus, depict scenes from the early to mid 19th Century. Many of the New York city scenes depicted include the New York waterways, such as "The Narrows from Staten Island", "The Ferry at Brooklyn", the view of New York from Staten Island and the view of New York from Weehawken, NJ.
    - "The Abbey" (Fulton Avenue near Hudson Avenue, 1835), circa 1850s-1870s (Box OS 7, Item 1)
    - "Brooklyn in 1853", circa 1850s-1860s (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - "Brooklyn in Winter" (Francis Guy), circa 1800s (Box Mold 2, Item 1)
    - Brooklyn, View of (1840), 1865 (Box OS 7, Item 2)
    - "The Ferry at Brooklyn", 1839 (Box OS 7, Item 3)
    - First Dutch Reformed Church ("The Old Bushwick Church L.I. Built in 1711"), 1864 (Box OS 7, Item 4)
    - Front Street, View of (1820), circa 1820s-1830s (Box OS 7, Item 5)
    - "Labon's Inn" (Flatbush Avenue, 1853), 1865 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - "The Narrows from Staten Island", 1837 (Box OS 7, Item 6)
    - "New York Bay from the Telegraph Station", 1838 (Box OS 7, Item 7)
    - New York from Staten Island: "View of...", circa 1835 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - New York from Weehawken, View of, 1839 (Box OS 7, Item 8)
    - "Old Bull's Head, Baker's Tavern" (Atlantic Avenue, 1842) (Box OS 7, Item 9)
    - Old Methodist Church in John Street, "A Correct View of the..." (1768), 1824 (Box OS 7, Item 10)
    - "Old Stone House at Gowanus" (1846), 1904 (Box OS 7, Item 11)
    - "Park and City Hall, New York" (by W.H. Bartlett), circa 1840s (Box Mold 2, Item 2)
    - Sheldon and Emburry Family Homes (114 Pierrepont Street and 62 Clark Street), circa 1910s-1930s (Box OS 7, Item 12)
    - Unidentified Building with Greenhouses, circa 1850s-1890s (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Sub-Series 3: Other Graphic Materials, circa 1830s-1880s; 0.5 Linear Feet in 1 document box and 1 oversized box.
    The Other Graphic Materials sub-series contains images that are not directly related to the Lefferts family and are not necessarily directly related to Brooklyn and New York City. Many of these materials were likely collected by the Fort Greene chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution during their tenure of stewardship over the Lefferts Historic House. Many of the materials in this sub-series are related to the American Revolutionary War. Of particular note are the prints of engravings depicting the Battle of Long Island. There are also several scenic prints of engravings of scenes from around New York State similar to the prints of engravings of scenes from Brooklyn and New York City in Sub-Series 2: Brooklyn and New York City Graphic Materials.
    - Nathanial Hawthorn (engraving w/ signature), 1854 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - New York State Scenic Prints, 1837-1838 (Box OS 7, Item 13)
      Moved to Mold Box 2: - "View From the Mountain House Catskills" by W.H. Bartlett and R. Brandard, 1839
    - Oliver Wendell Holmes, engraving, circa 1880 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Revolutionary War: Battle of Long Island, circa 1850s (Box OS 7, Item 14)
    - Revolutionary War: Capture of Major John Andre, 1845 (Box OS 7, Item 15)
    - Revolutionary War: Figures and Portraits, circa 1850s (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Series 7: Clippings, circa 1830s-1957; 1.25 Linear Feet In 1 document box and 1 oversized box.
  The Clippings series contains newsprint articles collected by the Lefferts family or on topics relevant to the Lefferts family and the Lefferts house. The majority of the materials are from the mid to late 19th Century and concern topics that include Brooklyn, the Civil War, Slavery, and retrospectives on the Battle of Long Island. The collection also contains the newsletters "The Forest Leaf" and "The Melodeon" which were produced for social service benefit purposes following the Civil War. Clippings from the 20th Century primarily concern the Lefferts house, the archaeological work associated with it, its eventual move to Prospect Park in 1918, and the place of the Lefferts family and house in early New York Dutch history. There are also early 20th Century articles on World War I and the assassination of President William McKinley.
  - Battle of Long Island, 1885, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Bedford Corners, 1887 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Brooklyn Bridge, 1883 (Box OS 2, Item 4)
  - Civil War, 1861-1865 (Box OS 2, Item 5)
  - Flatbush Town Hall, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - "The Forest Leaf, published for the benefit of the Festival In Aid of the Soldiers' Orphans" (Newsletter), 1865 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Lefferts, Allen, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Lefferts, John: Obituary, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Lefferts Family, circa 1890s, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Lefferts Houses, 1887-1950 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Five articles on the Lefferts House and family.
  - McKinley Assassination, 1901 (Box OS 2, Item 6)
  - "The Melodeon, Published for the Benefit of the Infant Department of the Reformed Dutch Church Sabbath-School" (Newsletter), 1865 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous Articles, circa 1830s-1890s (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Old Dutch Families in New York, 1874, 1890 (Box OS 2, Item 7)
  - Prospect Park (including Willink Entrance and Washington Irving Bust), circa 1870s (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Slavery, circa 1890s (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - World War I, 1917 (Box OS 2, Item 8)
- Series 8: Books and Scrapbooks, 1659-1917; 8 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 2 document boxes, and 4 oversized boxes.
  The books are arranged alphabetically by title and description.
  The Books and Scrapbooks series contains a variety of books which were either created by or maintained by the Lefferts family or acquired by the attendants of the Lefferts Historical House Museum. Books were kept within the collection if they had a strong connection to the Lefferts family or the Lefferts Historical House, if they had a strong connection to the life of the Lefferts particular to colonial American history, or if they included important inscriptions, marginalia, or notations and correspondence.
  There are a variety of religious books and bibles within the series including four very large bibles. Three of these bibles are in Dutch and date from the mid-17th Century to the mid-18th Century. The oversized Dutch Bibles are published by Hendrick and Jacob Keur and the oversized English Bible is published by Benjamin Kennicott. These family bibles were likely important pieces of the Lefferts household and many included handwritten accounts of family births, deaths, and marriages. Many of these documents have been moved to the Genealogical Material series but the Dutch Keur Bible from 1741 still includes some inscriptions of Cowenhoven family and Lefferts family births and deaths. In addition to the large family bibles, there are also several editions of the small Het Nieuwe Testament. The Reformed Dutch Church of Flatbush pointed out in its "Quarter Milllennial Anniversary" booklet (1904) that "it is probable that all the Dutch families own one or more of these books still" indicating the importance of this New Testament in Dutch to the religious families of Flatbush with Dutch heritage even into the 20th Century.
  There are some cookbooks and housekeeping guides included in this series. Most notable of these is the handwritten cookbook that was likely compiled by Maria Lott Lefferts and Gertrude Lefferts Vanderbilt. This cookbook also contains a loose page of recipes and some sewing threads that were left inside the book. Some of the printed cookbooks also contain handwritten recipes in the margins. The Receipts donated by the members of Saint Anna's Chapter of Saint Paul's Church in the Village of Flatbush includes a handwritten recipe for "Mother's Muffins" (page 42) and Housekeeping in old Virginia: Containing contributions from two hundred and fifty ladies in Virginia includes a handwritten recipe for "Sweet Pickled Fruit." Some more recipes, these used by Cornelia Stuyvesant, can be found in the Lefferts House and Ephemera series.
  Other notable books in the series include the arithmetic workbook of Maria Lott Lefferts, a scrapbook belonging to the Alexander family containing an assortment of collected and hand-drawn book and advertisement designs, the rare Batavische Arcadia by Johan van Heemskerk (1662), and several old-Dutch religious books from the 17th and 18th Centuries.
  - Alle de werken van Mr. Wilhelm Perkins, Zeer vermaarde, en voortreffelijke Ghod-Gheleerde (inscribed with: "Cornelius Van Der Veer"), 1659, 1796 (Box 6, Item 1)
  - Arithmetic Work Book of Maria Lott Lefferts, circa 1800s (Box 6, Item 2)
  - Batavische Arcadia by Johan van Heemskerk, 1662, 1781 (Box 6, Item 3)
  - Bybelsche History Liedekens by Joannes Kannewet (inscribed with "Peter Lefferts"), 1768 (Box 6, Item 4)
  - Catechizatie Ober den Heidelberghischen Catechismus der Gereformeerde Christelicke Religie by Petrum DeWitte, 1663 (Box 6, Item 5)
  - Cookbook (probably of Maria Lott Lefferts), 1800s (Box 6, Item 6)
  - Genealogy of the Lefferts family, 1650-1718 by Teunis G. Bergen, 1862, 1878 (Box 6, Item 7)
    Includes a write up on and letter to James Edward Jenkins from Commodore Grinnell and portrait photos of Cornelia Lefferts (Mrs. James Edward Jenkins), James Edward Jenkins, Lewis Lefferts Jenkins, and Georgette Pell (Mrs. Lewis Lefferts Jenkins)
  - Het Nieuwe Testament (inscribed with "Pieter De Marest"), 1717, 1728-1748 (Box 6, Item 8)
    Includes birth and death lists for Demarest family.